A Guide to the Richmond Musicians Club Archives 1916-1969
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Richmond Musicians Club Archives 1916-1969
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 222
5.2 linear feet
Richmond Musicians Club
Administrative Information
Access
No access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Audrey Black, respresenting the organization donated the collection to the department in 1986.
Historical Information
The Musicians Club of Richmond was founded in 1916 by a group of 30 women musical artists, teachers, and patrons, and was modeled after an earlier music organizations, the Wednesday Club (1893). It was primarily a woman's organization, although men could join as "associate" members. Although it began as a relatively small club, it quickly grew and by 1937, had more than 1000 members, sponsored a yearly opera performance, and concerts by many international artists. The Musicians Club provided the support for the founding and growth of the Richmond Symphony.
Organization members maintained that the Richmond's Musician's Club was a civic, cultural, and philanthropic group, and in no way a commercial venture. Its mission was to promote music in Richmond, as well as the musicians themselves, local and well known. The club cultivated a basic love and appreciation of music in and around the city, and sponsored public and private concerts, for club members, general audiences, and for charitable organizations, such as the Crippled Children's Hospital, the City Home, and the Soldier's Home. The first president was Francis Deane Williams.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains correspondence, minutes, newspaper clippings and other materials documenting the history of the Richmond Musicians Club for the years 1916 through 1969.
Arrangement
File units arranged alphabetically.
Contents List
- Correspondence 1962-1965 (Box-folder 1:1)
- Minutes 1927-1936 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Minutes 1936-1950 (Box-folder 1:3)
- Programs and Membership 1916-1955 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Treasurers Reports 1920-1950 (Box-folder 1:5)
- Minutes 1916-1921 (Box-folder 1:6)
- Minutes 1924-1932 (Box-folder 1:7)
- Program Committee 1923-1924 (Box-folder 2:1)
- Guest Book 1916-1929 (Box-folder 2:2)
- Minutes 1950-1955 (Box-folder 2:3)
- Scrapbook 1937-1939 (Box-folder 2:4)
- Scrapbook 1939-1940 (Box-folder 2:5)
- Scrapbook 1941-1943 (Box-folder 2:6)
- Scrapbook 1926-1936 (Box-folder 3:1)
- Scrapbook 1935-1937 (Box-folder 3:2)
- Scrapbook 1940-1941 (Box-folder 3:3)
- Scrapbook 1943-1945 (Box-folder 3:4)
- Scrapbook 1945-1946 (Box-folder 3:5)
- Scrapbook 1945-1948 (Box-folder 3:6)
- Scrapbook 1958-1960 (Box-folder 4:1)
- Scrapbook 1962-1964 (Box-folder 4:2)
- Scrapbook 1964-1967 (Box-folder 4:3)
- Scrapbook 1967-1969 (Box-folder 4:4)